怎么了，妈妈？
What's wrong, Mother?   Ruined.
毁了！毁了！
Ruined!
那个白痴把我们全都毁了！
That idiot has ruined us all!
我们将不得不离开罗马！
We shall have to leave Rome!
恺撒已经渡过了卢比肯河
Caesar has crossed the Rubicon.
他带着兵马踏上了意大利的土地
He's on ltalian soil under arms.
这可是叛国的行径
It's an act of gross treason.
只带一个军团…如果你不介意的话
With a single legion, if you please.
就不仅仅是叛国，而是自取灭亡的叛国之道
So not merely treason, but suicidal treason.
打完了吗，主人？
Will that be all, Domina?
你听说了吗？   嗯，很奇怪
Have you heard?   Mmm. Strange.
做出如此蠢的一件事
Afoolishthingtodo.
一个军团
One legion.
我很想知道恺撒在想什么
I wonder what he's thinking.
我不由得回想起当年我消灭那些伊利里亚人海盗的时候
I remember back when I destroyed the lllyrian pirates,
其中有个很特别的经验老道的…
there was one particular old sea snake
小型三层桨战船，如果我没记错的话
a Liburnian, if I recall.
别说那些伊利里亚人海盗了
Never mind the lllyrian pirates.
我们该怎么办？
What is to be done?
我已经发布命令了
I have already given word.
我的军团在集结
My legions are gathering.
你会把恺撒他们给捻碎，对吧？
And you'll crush him, yeah?
毫无疑问，那个可怜人死定了
Without question. The poor man is dead.
你将带领尤比恩骑兵，侦察
You are to take our Ubian cavalry and scout
由此到城市之间的路况以及防御的战略要点
all roads and defensive strongpoints between here and the city.
向前推进直到遇到抵抗
Advance until resistance is met.
如果遇到了公民
If and when civilians are encountered,
就把我们的这份布告递交给他们
deliver the enclosed proclamation.
如果没有遇到抵抗就直接把这份布告
If you encounter no resistance, go directly to the Forum
钉到元老会论坛的门上
and nail it to the Senate door.
长官
Sir.
不允许进行烧杀掠夺
There will be no rapine, pillage or burning.
有问题吗？   没有，长官
Any questions?   None, sir.
执行命令吧
That will be all.
你手下的这个乌瑞纳斯怎么这么闷？
What makes your man vorenus so morose?
他只是对此有所抵触
He is stonewall Catonian.
他认为我们犯了滔天大罪
He thinks we've committed a terrible crime,
是逆天而行
a mighty sacrilege,
应该被神严厉的惩罚
and shall be severely punished by the Gods.
他没准是对的   只有我们失败了才有罪
He may be right.   It's a crime if we lose.
而胜利者是无罪的
If we win, it isn't.
我不过是在要求我的合法权利，安东尼
I am merely pursuing my legitimate rights, Antony.
当然   你认为我们可以信任他吗？
Of course.   Do you think we can trust him?
谁？   卢西尔斯·乌瑞纳斯
Who?   Lucius vorenus.
噢，他是老13军团的人了
Oh. Deep 13th, him.
鹰旗就是他奋不顾身找回来的
He'd follow the eagle up Pluto's ass.
我跟你说过别来这里的
I told you not to come here.
我很想看看我的儿子
I had to see my son.
你已经看到了，马上离开
You've seen him. Now go.
再也别回来了
And stay away.
帮帮我，内奥比
Help me, Niobe.
我都快要疯狂了
I'm going insane.
你不能就如此抛弃我
You can't forsake me.
我可以的
I do.
我不会放弃的
I won't give up. Don't think I will.
你爱过我一次，就会再次爱上我的
You loved me once, you will love me again.
我从来就没有爱上过你
I never loved you.
你可以试着欺骗自己，但不要欺骗我
Lie to yourself if you want, but don't lie to me.
离开吧
Stay away.
你知道你将永远无法见到你的丈夫
You know you will never see your husband now,
你知道的，对吗？
you know that, eh?
他跟那些人都死定了
Him and all the rest of them are doomed.
你别那么肯定
You don't know that.
大家都知道会这样
Everybody knows that.
或许会吧，但是我立过誓言（结婚时）
That may be, but I made a vow.
离开
Go.
我向冥神发誓，如果你不离开
I swear to Dis, if you don't go
没什么事，他就走
It's all right. He's going.
快离开吧
Just go.
你答应过你不在见他
You promised you would never see him again.
我没叫他来，我让他走
I didn't want him here. I told him to go.
看起来可不像是这样
It didn't look like that.
你可以跟爸爸说出真相，不是你的错
You could tell Papa the truth. It's not your fault.
如果你跟我向他说…
If you and I spoke to him
永远不要，你发过誓的
Never. You have sworn.
你以为他战死了，爸爸会理解的
You thought he was dead. Papa will understand.
他会把我们全杀了
He will kill us all.
你常说你是花丛中的老手
You   you often say that you are adept with women.
可不是闲谈时的自夸
No idle boast neither.
从纳波到底比斯都有女孩子在晚上尖叫着我的名字
There are girls from Nabo to Thebes that scream my name by night.
我不需要你的床上技巧
I have no need of your coital expertise.
我问的是有关爱情的东西
My question more concerns their... affections.
我可以在这方面给你一些指导
I'm your man for that to boot.
我老婆，她…
My wife, she...
你听到过她说，她恨我
You heard what she said, she hates me.
你到底想问什么？
What's your question?
非常明显，我如何能够让她不恨我？
How do I stop her from hating me, obviously?
这可不是显而易见的问题
It's not obvious.
我以为你特意的让她恨你呢
I thought you were making her hate you with a purpose.
那根本不是我的目的，我为什么要那么做？
That was not my intent at all. Why would I do that?
我怎么知道，你是个聪明人
I don't know. You're the clever one, you.
你可能会有无数个理由这么作
There might have been 1,000 reasons.
我爱她，希望她也爱我，
I love her, and I require
而不是仅仅把我当成一个劳动力
that she love me also, else I am merely her slave.
对此我无法容忍
I cannot tolerate that.
那么，是什么让你关心她怎么看待你
Well, what care you what she feels for you
如果我们在这一两个礼拜内就会死掉
if we're all going to die this week or next?
我们很可能会死掉，但是我死后谁来祭奠我的名字
And so we are, but who will honor my name when I am gone?
谁能为我向地狱女神跟冥王献上祭品？
Who will pay Proserpina and Pluto for my keep?
谁会为我的墓碑撒上红酒？
Who will pour wine upon my grave?
如果真的变成那样的话，我会做的
If it comes to that, I shall do the honors.
这是最起码我可以做的
It's the least I could do.
谢谢
Thank you.
但是这不是一回事
But it's not the same thing.
此外…
Besides...
你也会一起死掉的
you'll be dead too.
我在计划今晚的一个小聚会，我需要你…
I'm planning on having a small party this evening and I'll need you to
你用香水了？
Are you wearing perfume?
一点点而已
Just a dab.
真是让人讨厌
It's horrid.
马粪味更适合你
Horseshit suits you much better.
现在我需要更多的人在外面守卫
Now I need you to get more men to stand guard outside
当我的客人来得时候向他们问候
to greet my guests when they arrive.
一个聚会？ 现在举行聚会是一个明智的举动吗？
A party? Is that wise, given how things are?
香水的建议？ 还想有点什么建议？
Perfume, advice   whatever next?
我只想说庞贝的手下正蠢蠢欲动
I'm just saying Pompey's mob is out for blood.
最好低调点   低调？
It's best to lay low.   Lay low?
我可不是一头蜥蜴，我永远不会被威胁
I'm not a lizard. I will not be intimidated.
如你所愿，不过价格高点
As you like. Cost you extra though.
你的报酬已经足够好了
You've been paid quite adequately already.
更多的人手需要花费的更多
More men cost more.
我会让卡斯特跟你谈的
I will tell Castor to speak with you.
我并不是想要更多的钱
I don't want more money.
那么，你想要什么呢？
Well, what do you want then?
你知道我想要什么
You know what I want.
就是像这样的…
Something like that.
你忘记你的地位了   我的地位是来自于我的家族的
You forget your place.   My place is with my family.
给个命令，我就会发动他们
Say the word, and I'll go to them.
把你的事情做到我满意，然后…
Do your job to my satisfaction and...
我想你是会得到适当的回报的
I'll see that you're properly rewarded.
谢谢，主人
Thank you, Domina.
庞贝的先锋
Pompey's outriders.
他的军团应该也不远了
His legions won't be far behind.
我们跟剩下的13军团的弟兄们在市集日就会被钉在十字架上
Us and the rest of the 13th will be on crosses by market day.
感谢神，我父亲没有活着看见他的儿子以叛国者的身份而死去
Thank the Gods my father didn't live to see his son die a traitor.
最后现在就去死，嗯？ 走！
Best to die now then, eh? Go on.
等等，我们不是来交锋的
Wait! We're not here to fight.
“向前推进直到遇到抵抗”
"Advance until resistance is met."
这是我们的命令，也是我们所要做的
That is our orders. That is what we do.
为什么不呢？ 弟兄们都准备好了，对吧
Why not? The boys are ready, aren't you, boys?
让我们冲吧，来吧
Let's have a go. Come on!
不准交战！
No fight!
不！不准交战！该死的白痴们！
No! No fight now! Damned idiot!
列队防守
Form up and defend!
记住你们受过的训练！
Remember your training!
摆盾牌！
Shields!
坚守阵地   站稳了
Hold your ground!   Stand tall!
站稳了
Hold positions!
回来，懦夫
别动，懦夫，回来！
Stay in place, you cowards!
恺撒的斥候已到罗马城30英里外
Caesar's scouts are only 30 miles from Rome.
30英里？
30 miles?
他的推进速度很惊人
His speed is uncanny.
当然，他的人手不多
Of course, he has only a very few men,
所以能够快速推进
which makes a fast pace easier.
他领导的与其说是军队不如说是武装的暴徒
He is not leading an army so much as an armed gang.
是非常无规矩，无道德的，甚至
It is all highly irregular, unethical even.
现在甚至都不是战争的季节
Gods, it is not even the war season.
他没有想要直接攻击罗马吧？
Surely he does not think to attack Rome directly?
我认为这正是他所想要做的
I think that is exactly what he will do.
他怎么能够期待成功呢？
How can he hope to succeed?
目前的问题是
The problem is, at this moment,
我们只有3个武装军团能够保卫这个城市
we have only three legions in arms for the defense of the city.
当然，3个军团已经足够了
Surely, three is more than enough.
通常的情况下是的，但是大部分战士
Normally that would be true, but most of the men
都是新征召的，就像被斥候打散了的那些一样
are raw recruits like those who fled from the scouts.
而剩下的都是打过高卢的老兵
The rest are veterans of Gaul.
恺撒过去的手下不能信任
Caesar's men   not reliable.
罗马不设防了！
Rome is undefended!
我的军团正在尽快的集结
My legions are mustering as swiftly as possible,
但是需要最少4天时间
but it will take at least four days
才能成型并且保卫这个城市
to assemble a force capable of defending the city.
恺撒的队伍只有不到2天的路程了
Caesar is two days away.
你真是一针见血
You touch it with a needle.
我们现在怎么办？
What do we do now then?
我们必须进行一个战术撤退到南方
We must make a tactical retreat to the south.
一个战术撤退，提醒你们
A tactical retreat, mind you.
离开这个城市？
Leave the city?
朱诺神后的灰孙子，难道你疯了吗？
Juno's cunt! Do you run mad?
你不能用这种语气跟我说话
You cannot speak to me in that tone.
朋友们，还是让我们集中关注手头的麻烦吧
My friends, let us cleave to the matter at hand.
除了撤退，没有别的路可以选了吗？
Is there no alternative to retreat then?
没有，我们应该撤到迦非尼尔
None. We shall withdraw to Corfinium
在那里重新集结我的军团
and rally my legions there.
一旦他们集结起来，整顿好军序
Once they are gathered and in good order,
我们就能轻松的把罗马城夺回来
we will simply retake the city.
恺撒在春天前都无法得到援军
Caesar has no hope of reinforcement until spring.
意大利的城市都会对他关上大门
The towns of ltaly will close their gates to him.
在人力跟物力资源上我们已经立于不败之地
We will have an unassailable advantage in men and resources.
那么事实上，这根本不是个令人羞辱的溃退
So in fact, this is not a humiliating defeat at all
而是个罕有的胜利？
but a rare species of victory?
卡托，让你自己冷静下来，你对军事上的东西一无所知
Calm yourself, Cato. You lack understanding of things military,
你将会看到，我的战术
else you would see that my actions
将是无比完美的在任何时候
have been perfectly correct at all times.
你毫不抵抗的就放弃罗马
You have lost Rome without unsheathing your sword.
你已经失去罗马了！
You have lost Rome!
庞贝的手下的那些杂碎在我们的门外
Pompeian scum at our very door!
真让人无法忍受
It's intolerable.
如果泰门跟他的手下不在这里的话，他们会把房子都烧了
If Timon and his men weren't here, they'd be burning down the house.
哦，他们没有那么多精神
Oh, they are not that energetic.
这场自杀式的谋反使所有人都变得跟我们敌对起来
This suicidal rebellion has turned everyone against us.
我发誓，如果恺撒现在就在这里的话
I swear, if Caesar were here now,
我会狠狠的刺向他的脖子
I would stab him in the neck.
他把我们都给毁了   对此我不是很确定
He has ruined us.   I'm not so sure of that.
但是我想庞贝的地位也不稳固了
But I think Pompey's position is deceptively weak.
想，想，想，这就是全部你做的事情，你这个笨小孩
Think think think   that's all you do, you silly boy.
我们所以的朋友都抛弃了我们
All our friends have abandoned us,
那帮胆小鬼，我们优利亚家族现在人见人恶了
cowards that they are. We Julii are lepers now.
别太夸张了，不是你所有的朋友都抛弃了你
Let us not exaggerate, not all of your friends have deserted you.
这是会被记住的
Andthatwill be remembered.
你是我们忠诚的好友
You are good loyal people.
虽然放弃恺撒非常有诱惑力
It's very tempting to abandon Caesar,
但是如果现在这么做的话，那我们就会被看成
but to do so now, well, that would look like we're mere...
顺应大潮流的奴隶
slaves to fashion.
你们留下来保护房子
You're staying to protect the house
但是想都别想我跟你们的主人无法回来
but don't think for a moment that your master and I will not return.
我们最晚下月初就回来
We will be back by the Calends at the latest.
当我回来的时候
And when I do return, those of you I find
如果我发现你们当中有人没有尽好自己的责任的话，他就会付出生命的代价
have not done their utmost duty will pay with their lives.
将军，你的卫队已经准备完毕
General, your escort is ready.
格涅乌斯
Gnaeus.   Mmm?
多里奥，卫队准备好了吗？
Durio, is the escort ready?
准备好了，长官   那么出发吧
Ready, sir.   Away then.
丈夫，国库呢？
Husband, the treasury?
哦，对啊
Yes, of course.
多里奥，你必须
Durio. You must secure
确保国库黄金的安全
as much of the treasury gold as possible.
分遣队走，打开卡比托奈山丘神殿拱顶
Take a detachment and open up the Capitoline vaults.
时间不多了，尽你所能吧
There's not much time, so do what you can.
让我们装作是奥德修斯跟他的朋友
Let's pretend we're Odysseus and his friends,
偷偷摸摸的溜出独眼巨人的洞穴
creeping out of the Cyclops' cave.
我们必须像老鼠一样安静，好吗？
We must be quiet as little mice, all right?
Come.
对这一切我很抱歉   别这么说
Sorry about all this.   Do not say so.
我不介意一点小小的刺激
I don't mind a little excitement.
一切都会好的，我向你保证
All will be well, I assure you.
我对此毫不怀疑
I have no doubt.
出发
Let's away.
记住，别搞出声音
And remember,, nosound.
打开它！
Break it down!
真是仁慈
Here's a mercy.
为了不让我们活在羞愧和不荣誉中
Instead of living out our lives in shame and disgrace,
一群疯狂的暴徒要强奸，殴打我们
we are to be raped and beaten
要把我们撕成碎片
and torn limb from limb by a raving mob.
这些畜生我想不会放过你们的
These brutes will not let you pass, I think.
你晚上可以留下，如果你想的话
You may stay the night if you want.
谢谢，我们对此很高兴
We would be delighted, thank you.
等等，走错了
Wait wait. Wrong way.
亚壁门在右边
The Appian gate is to the right.
我们不去亚壁
We're not going to the Appian.
什么？
What?
当然，你取悦女人最好的方法是
Of course, your best method for pleasing a woman
敌人温暖且还在跳动的心脏
is the warm, beating heart of an enemy.
女人们会说她们不喜欢，其实是喜欢的
Women will say they don't like it, but they do.
会让她们像雨季那样潮湿
It makes them wet as October.
这解决不了问题
That doesn't answer.
那么试试这个，跟她谈谈
Well, failing that, talk to her.
谈谈
Talk.
说什么？   说什么无关紧要
But of what?   That doesn't matter.
关键在于你的声调嗓音
It's all about the tone of the voice.
你应该就像给一匹烈马上马鞍一样
You pretend like you're putting a saddle on a skittish horse.
“这儿宝贝，嘘，来吧”
"There, honey. Shh, come now."
你知道的，就像这样
You know, that sort of thing.
就这些？   还有什么？
That's all?   What else?
噢！任何时候都跟她说她很漂亮
Oh! Tell her she is beautiful all the time.
每次你见到她的时候都跟她说她很漂亮
Tell her she's beautiful every time you see her,
即使她不是
even when she's not.
还有什么？
And what else?
噢！还有，非常重要的是…
Oh! Also, very important...
当您们行周公之礼的时候，她小妹妹上方有个地方
when you couple with her, there's a spot just above her cunny
就像个小纽扣
it's like a little button.
注意要关注到那里
Now, attend to that button,
那么她就会很享受的
and she will open up like a flower.
你怎么知道她那里的？
How do you know this of her?
所以的女人都有
All women havethem.
随便问一个就知道了
Ask anyone.
Ho ho ho, very pretty. Come up behind!
Come with us!   Sit up here!
You can make me happy!
It'll make me happy.
哦，哦哦，小美丽，跟上来
Here you go. Up you go. Come on!
我会杀掉奥克塔维娅，然后玛如拉来做了我
I will kill Octavia, and Merula tends to me,
但是如果她做不到，我被活抓了，那么你必须要杀了我
but if she cannot, and I am taken alive, then you must kill me.
然后你必须自杀
And then you must kill yourself.
你活下去将是不恰当的
Your survival would be inappropriate.
我不会想着活下去的，主人
I would not think of living, Domina.
屋大维，你喜欢谁杀你？
Octavian, who would you prefer kills you?
我已经大的能够照顾自己了
I am old enough to take care of myself.
噢，我勇敢的小男人
Oh, that's my brave little man.
赛维莉娅…
Servilia...
我的人能够给你任何协助吗？
can my people be of any assistance to you?
谢谢，但是我相信我们能够自我解决
Thank you but I'm sure we can manage by ourselves somehow.
很好
very well.
母亲，我倾向不是你来杀我
Mother, I would rather it were not you killed me
如果你没有异议的话
if you have no objection.
为什么不，你不会还在生我的气吧
Why ever not? You can't still be angry with me.
是个命令吗？   仁慈的女神啊！
Is that an order?   Bona Dea!
我感觉你从来没有听过我说
I feel like you have never listened
冥府守门狗正在向我们嚎叫，你还在用你那些无稽
Cerberus is howling for us, and still you plague me
感觉来烦我？
with your ridiculous feelings?
如果你让我跟格雷毕斯再婚
If you had only let Glabius and I remarry
噢，什么都是格雷毕斯！
Oh, always Glabius!
我唾骂格雷毕斯！我撒尿在那个可怜虫身上！
I spit on Glabius! I piss on the wretch!
哦，没错，母亲，就像你活着那样死去
Oh, that's right, Mother, die as you have lived
灵魂中满是恶毒   都听着！
poison brimming in your soul.   Listen!
我不会跟你吵，卡斯特要确认割断奥克塔维娅的喉咙
I'll not argue with you. Castor, be sure to cut Octavia's throat
在你割断我的喉咙之前    卡斯特请让我母亲来做
before you cut mine.   Please, Castor, let Mother do it.
我不想回绝她最后一件乐事
I won't deny her one last pleasure.
就不像个女儿了   都听着！
It would be undaughterly.   Listen!
执政官格涅乌斯·庞贝·麦格纳斯已经离开这个城市了
Consul Gnaeus Pompey Magnus has left the city.
他命令所有贵族跟武士们也这么做
He commands all noblemen and knights to do likewise.
留下来的人会被认为是
Those that remain will be considered
罗马帝国的敌人   懦夫！
enemies of Rome.   Cowards!
你听说了
You heard, then.
真不知道那会带来什么好处
Don't know what good that will do.
任何人想进来，他们就能够进来
Anyone wants to get in, they'll get in.
搭把手，好吗？
Give us a hand, will you?
看起来，你男人总归会回来
So your man will be back after all, looks like.
看起来是
It looks like.
你似乎对此不是很高兴
You don't sound too happy about it.
我当然很高兴，他是我丈夫   如果你这么说的话
Of course I'm happy. He's my husband.   If you say so.
很抱歉
I'm sorry.
我只是说说而已
I was just talking.
我说的太多了
I talk too much.
我不知道，莉萨
I don't know, Rissa.
我尽最大可能去爱他，我确实是
I try my best to love him, I do.
我不知道我是否希望他回来
I don't know whether I want him to come back.
我不会相信如果我没有亲眼见到
I would not credit it if I had not seen it myself.
庞贝的人放弃了这个城市，放弃了罗马
Pompey's men deserting the city, deserting Rome,
一半的元老都上马跑了
half the Senate ahorse.
毫无疑问一个滑稽的场面
A comical sight no doubt.
神们啊
Gods.
我们处于一个该死的尴尬局面
We are in a damned awkward position.
如果我们留下…
If we stay...
我们就是拥护恺撒，拥护叛军
we are declaring for Caesar, for rebellion.
如果我们离开，我们…我们就是追随庞贝以及元老院
And if we go, we   we are with Pompey and the Senate.
没有可以妥协的余地   那么你的决定是什么？
There is no middle ground.   So what is the answer?
恺撒是我们最亲爱的朋友，但是他正在做的是…
Caesar is our dearest friend, but what he is doing is
我不知道
I do not know.
你必须决定
You must decide.
那么就是庞贝
Pompey then.
我们必须跟庞贝走
We must go with Pompey.
共和比任何朋友都重要
The Republic is more important than any friendship.
你同意吗？   那是你的决定
Do you agree?   It's your decision.
那么就是庞贝
Pompey then.
我们没有时间可以浪费了
We have no time to lose.
告诉你的侍女们准备离开，越快越好
Tell your women to be ready to leave as soon as possible.
我不走
I'm not leaving.
你是什么意思？
What do you mean?
我等恺撒等了8年
I've waited eight years for Caesar.
我现在不能离开
I cannot leave now.
如果我要走，你不能留下
You cannot stay, not if I go.
我当然可以留下
Of course I can stay.
我可做我想做的事
I can do as I wish.
目前，留下来的都是罗马的敌人
Mother, all who stay are enemies of Rome.
庞贝已经这么宣布了   恺撒有可能会胜利
Pompey has declared it.   Caesar might prevail.
是的，他可能统治罗马1个礼拜1个月，甚至1年
Yes, he might rule Rome for a week, a month, a year even,
但是另外一些有野心的人就会
but then some other ambitious man
杀了他，取代他的位置
will kill him and take his place,
那时你就是暴君的情妇
and you then will be the mistress of a dead tyrant.
母亲，我们知道什么会发生在她们身上
Mother, we know what happens to them.
这还是让神们来决定吧
That is for the gods decide.
我无法自拔的爱着他
I cannot help loving him.
够了，母亲！
A va, Mother!
你…你是彻底被你的欲望所蒙蔽了
You   you are blinded by untapped lust.
我会在市集上帮你买个又好又大的昔勒尼人，然后解决问题
I'll get you a good big Cyrenian at the market and have done with it.
你最好走吧
You'd better go.
别生我的气
Don't be angry with me.
我们可能要分离很长时间
We may be parted for a long time.
来
Come.
再见，母亲
Goodbye, Mother.
再见，我的宝贝
Goodbye, my love.
你的女儿离开了
Your daughter left.
什么时候？
When?
刚刚，我找人跟着她了
Just now. I put a boy to following her.
我会中止这个没意义的事情的
I'll put a stop to this nonsense.
派你的人   什么？
Fetch your men.   What?
现在
Now.
为什么你还没有离开城里
Why have you not left the city?
现在不安全
I could not leave without seeing you.
大家都知道现在你们跟着庞贝
It's not safe for you. Everyone knows you're with Pompey.
别着急，我在日出前就走
Don't fret. I'll be gone by sunrise.
这是我所有的钱   谢谢
That's all I have.   Thank you,
不过我们不是打劫
but this is not a robbery.
阿提娅   我会给你点时间
Atia.   I'll give you a moment,
如果你想跟神祷告的话
if there are gods you'd like to speak to.
一个请求…放过我的手下
One favor   let my men live.
对不起，上头有命令
Sorry. It's orders.
把你的剑给我
Give me your sword.
那些星星都是什么？
What are they, the stars?
星星？ 天球上的洞而已
Stars? Holes in the celestial spheres.
天堂的光通过那些洞照射进来
Holes through which the light of the heavens shine.
那些洞有多大？
How big are these holes?
非常大
They're big.
之所以看起来这么小，是因为他们离我们好几百英里远
They only seem small to us because they're hundreds of miles away.
大的足够让男人通过？
Big enough for a man to climb through?
我猜是
I suppose.
但首先人是无法到达那里的
But man would never be able to get up there in the first place.
我看不出为什么不行   怎么去呢？
I don't see why not.   How?
他可以抓住一只巨鸟
He could hold onto a giant bird.
像那样是不行的
It doesn't work like that.
为什么不行？   这是哲学的东西
Why not?   It's philosophy.
很难解释的
It's hard to explain.
是吗，纽摩，那真是不必要的
Really, Numa, that's quite unnecessary.
我请求你站起来
I beg you stand.
这里不需要太拘谨
There shall be no formality here,
不是在像我们这样的老朋友之间
not between old friends like us.
千倍的感激，阿提娅
Athousand gratitudes, Atia.
我们卑谦的寻求您家族的保护以及友谊
We humbly seek the protection and friendship of your family.
不幸的是，有人说
Sadly, there are some people who say
我是庞贝那一派的人
that I am of the Pompeian faction.
你不是吗？
Are you not?
所有庞贝的党羽早已逃走了
All of Pompey's faction have long since fled.
你只是因为害怕你的工厂跟仓库被抢劫才留下来的吧
You stay for fear your factories and storehouses will be looted.
我向你保证，不是那样的
I assure you, that's not true
卡斯特
Castor.
5,000 便士   那么多？
5,000 denarii.   That much?
我，我…   请不要让我们变得那么低俗
l l     Please, let us not be vulgar.
我会立刻安排的
I'll make the arrangements immediately.
你的那个手下多里奥在哪里？
Where is your man Durio?
他迟到了很久了
He is long overdue now.
多里奥是我最优秀的手下
Durio is the best man I have.
他不会出错的
He won't fail.
但如果有问题，那么怎么办？
But if not, what then?
我们怎么给军团发饷，怎么喂饱他们？
How do we pay the legions? How do we feed them?
我还没有那种想法，卡托，你像女人一样烦人
I have not the least idea. You fret like a woman, Cato.
多里奥会带着足够多的黄金来维持我们的军团
Durio will return with more than enough gold to feed and pay the legions.
不论怎样，我们会在春天前回到罗马
By any road we'll be back in Rome before spring,
别担心了
so stop worrying.
真是莫名其妙
It makes no sense.
现在我们应该被阻止了
We should have been stopped by now.
为什么罗马没有防御？
Why is Rome not defended?
我们的弟兄们把他们吓跑了，嗯？
Our boys scared 'em off, eh?
共和国的战士是不会跑的
Soldiers of the Republic do not run,
所以肯定是个战略或者计谋   那么肯定是个好计谋
so it must be a stratagem or trick.   Then it's a good trick.
除非神们已经放弃了罗马
Unless the gods have abandoned Rome.
如果战神在关注
If Mars was watching,
他不会允许如此不荣誉的事情发生的
he would not allow such a disgrace.
有可能他在忙着掷骰子而没有注意到这里
Well, maybe he was having a crap and missed it.
那种无礼已经引导我们到达这个糟糕的困境
It's that sort of disrespect that has led us to this sad pass.
如果神们不被尊敬，他们为什么要帮助我们？
If the gods are not respected, then why should they help us?
还是没有部队
Still no troops.
我期待他们会从侧翼袭击我们
They will have flanked us, I expect.
或许那些赶牛车的人知道点什么
Perhaps these drovers know something.
Whoa.
神圣的公民们   队长
Salve, citizens.   Captain.
你们从城里来？   是的
You come from the city?   We do.
那里现在怎样？   你们是恺撒的手下
How goes it there?   You're Caesar's men.
是的   财富女神已经为你们布满了金蛋
We are.   Fortune spreads her legs for you.
庞贝已经逃了，城是你们的了
Pompey has fled. The city is yours.
庞贝为什么逃走？   对他来说你们太快了
Why would Pompey flee?   You boys were too fast for him.
他没有足够的时间招集他的军队
He couldn't raise his armies quick enough.
他跟他的手下撤向南方，元老院也跟去了
Him and his men are retreating south, and the Senate with 'em.
看吧？ 错了一次
See? Wrong for once.
那么，嗯，享受你们的胜利吧
Well, uh, enjoy your victory boys.
那个女孩值多少钱？   不卖
How much do you want for the girl?   Not for sale.
货车里是什么？
What's in the wagon?
谷物   让我们看看，士兵
Grain.   Show us, soldier.
这里没有士兵
There's no soldiers here.
我的错，你们全部穿着士兵的鞋子
My mistake. You all wear the soldier's boot,
所以我假设你们是士兵，但是我错了
so I assumed you are soldiers, but I'm wrong.
但是为什么会有9个士兵看着一辆装着谷物的货车？
But why would nine good soldiers be guarding a grain wagon?
我不需要给你看什么
I don't have to show you nothing.
Hyah!
我永远的忠诚，主人
My fidelity always, Domina.
我不喜欢去怀疑你，庞帝拉丝
I do not like to doubt you, Proculus,
但是我上一次在早晨的召集中看见你已经是年前的事了
but it's an age since I have seen you at my morning levy.
或许你是不太舒服，大脖子病是吗？
Perhaps you have been unwell. Goiters is it?
啊，嗯…如您所说，大脖子病
Ah, uh   goiters, as you say.
又胖又贪婪的男人经常会发现这个
Fat, greedy men often find it so.
我应该杀一只猫头鹰好让你的健康继续
I shall kill an owl that your good health continue.
说明白点，你个奴才
Speak sense, you creature.
这是什么可怕的交易啊，把尸体运到人家的大门
What vile trade is this, bringing corpses to honest doors?!
把它带走
Take it away!
看看你们都做了什么？
See what you have done?
这城市是不设防的
The city's unguarded.
是真的，共和国正在沦陷
It's true then. The Republic is fallen.
但是天还是在上，地还是在下
Yet the sky is still above us, and the earth still below.
真是奇怪   众神一点都不急
Strange.   The gods are in no hurry.
他们会花费时间慢慢的折磨我们
They will take their time in tormenting us.
让我们回去看看货车里有什么，顺便解开那个女孩
Let's go back and see what's in that wagon. Untie that girl.
不是我们关心的，我们要执行命令
Not our concern. We follow orders.
向前推进直到遇到抵抗
Advance until resistance is met.
但是那个可怜的女孩…   你要履行你的义务
But that poor girl     You will do your duty.
你真是个刻薄的混蛋，那就是你的问题
You are a mean bastard, that's your problem.
你不会得到爱
You've no love in you.
你可以向内奥比甜言蜜语，但是不会有任何作用
You can talk sweet as you like to Niobe, it won't do you any good.
她一个字都不会相信的
She won't believe a word.
宝贝，你终于醒了
Ercule, you wake at last.
我很担心
I was worried.
来点水？
Water?
我可怜的宝贝
My poor baby.
哦，那一切都不是梦啊
Oh, it was not a dream then.
格雷毕斯死了
Glabius is dead.
他死了
He is.
我很难过
I'm sorry.
你为什么那样看着我？
Why do you look at me like that?
怎样？
Like what?
好像是我…
As ifl
是你吗？   你怎么能够问我这个问题？
Did you?   How can you ask me that question?
是你吗？
Did you?
我才没有！
I did not!
而且我很痛苦因为你居然有
And I'm tortured that you would harbor
那种可怕的想法   看着我！
such a horrible notion.   Look at me!
女儿，我以所有祖先的面目发誓
Daughter, I swear on the masks of all my ancestors
我什么都没做…
that I had nothing
我跟格雷毕斯的死毫无关系
nothing to do with the killing of Glabius.
母亲，你认为是谁做的呢？
Who do you think did it, Mother?
街上到处是尸体
The streets are full of corpses.
任何人都有可能
It could have been anyone.
“本诏告来自于盖乌斯·优利乌斯·恺撒
"These are the words of Gaius Julius Caesar,
维纳斯的直系子孙，高卢总督
direct descendant of venus, Proconsul of Gaul,
显赫的北方军团统帅
Glorious lmperato of the northern legions.
公民们，我已经回到意大利
Citizens, I have returned to ltaly
我的目的仅仅是为自己讨回合法的，道德的权利
with the sole intention of claiming my legal and moral rights.
我并不渴求非法的权力
I have no desire for unlawful powers.
我不会宣布任何人为敌
I will name no man an enemy
既便他们这么做了
who does not so declare himself.
经管如此，这些敌人的财产也不会被谋夺
Even so, the property of those enemies will not be appropriated
他们的家人也不会被涉及
and their person will remain inviolate
只要他们的反对能够是和平进行的
as long as their opposition be peaceful.
此外，对于任何拿起武器反对我的人
Moreover, to any man that has taken arms against me
只要现在感到后悔，我很乐于特赦他们
and now regrets it, I gladly offer total amnesty.
但是，那些继续使用暴力
However, those that continue to use violence
来反对我合法权利的人
to oppose my legal rights,
他们会得到他们应受的惩罚
they shall receive that which they seek to give.
在朱庇特主神的保护下
Under the auspices of Jupiter Capitolinus,
这就是盖乌斯·优利乌斯·恺撒的诏告”
these are the words of Gaius Julius Caesar."
你在干吗？
What are you doing?
我已经完成了我的任务，而且我的罪孽已经够深厚了
I have done my duty and I have sinned enough.
我离职
I resign.
这是开小差
That's desertion.
我已经是个叛国的造反者了
I am a traitor and a rebel,
为什么不再加上个逃脱者的名字？
why not a deserter as well?
你不能就这样离开13军团
You can't just leave the 13th.
再见，波罗
Goodbye, Pullo.
至维纳斯，生育的主宰者，我为您献上这份祭礼
To venus, the birth giver, I make this sacrifice.
我是乌瑞纳斯氏族的卢西尔斯，斯特拉迪纳部落
I am Lucius of the vorenian clan, tribe of Stellatina,
前任的13军团主力步兵团
formerly First Spear Centurion to the Prime Cohort
矛兵百夫长
of the 13th Legion.
我有一个妻子
I have a wife.
她的名字叫内奥比
Her name is Niobe.
维纳斯，请让她像我爱她那样爱我
venus, let her love me as I love her.
我奉献我的血，希望能够达到目的
I give my blood to make it so.
对不起，我没有吓你的意思
Sorry, I didn't mean to scare you.
你真漂亮
You're very beautiful.
出于无知，我想看看我是否没有
I've come to see that it may be, through ignorance,
像我应该的那样来对待你
that I have not treated you as I should.
像我应该的那样来对待你   请不要
As I should treat you.   Please, don't.
我们结婚的时候你还只有13岁
When we married you had only 13 summers,
而且我很快的就离开了
and soon enough I was gone.
但是你现在已经是个女人了，而我对女人一无所知
But now you are a woman, and I know nothing of women.
我所知道的都是士兵的东西
Soldiering is all I know.
很明显是没用的
Which is not useful.
我曾经是如此的郁闷，冷淡跟不信任
I have been sullen and untrusting and cold.
但是我不是石头做的
But I am not made of stone.
我可以改
I can change.
我可以用我女儿的儿子来发誓
I will swear on the life of my daughter's son.
我会改的，如果你是这么希望的话
I will change, if you would have it so.
请告诉我如果你不愿意的话
Please, speak if you would not have it so,
我会离开并且不会恨你
and I will leave without rancor.
是我做错了事   怎么呢？
It is I have done wrong.   How so?
我是…
I am...
我没有能够…
I have not been...
过去的已经过去了
The past is gone.
我们可以重新开始吗？
Can we start again?
Ha!
我不得不赞赏你
I applaud you.
你就要像一个血淋淋的征服者一样进入罗马了
You're about to enter Rome as a bloodstained conqueror,
但是你看起来就像一杯水那样平静
and yet you look as calm as a cup of water.
我很高兴我看起来如此
I am glad I appear so.
加咯斯，来点更高兴的音乐
Gracchus, something more cheerful.
翻译:TLF字幕组